Guide to the Sol Feinstone Papers and Historical Documents Collection TAM.036
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Sol Feinstone Papers and Historical Documents Collection
1770-1950
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Feinstone, Sol, 1888-1980
TAM.036
1 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box and 1 oversize flat box
Sol Feinstone was a socialist, successful businessman, and a collector of historical documents. This collection contains correspondence between Sol Feinstone and Roman Rosdolsky, primarily in connection with Rosdolsky's manuscript "Friedrich Engeles und das Problem der Geschichtslosen Volker." The collection also contains twenty-eight documents including signed letters by notable figures such as Eugene V. Debs, Petr Kropotkin, Vladimir Illich Lenin, and notes by Karl Marx. There are also approximately a dozen documents associated with the French Revolution and a surveyor's report from 1770 of Blidworth, England.
Historical/Biographical Note
Sol Feinstone, born Solomon Bialagrudsky in 1888 in Lithuania, migrated to the United States in 1902. A socialist, he became a successful businessman and a collector of historical documents.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series, both of which are arranged alphabeticly by topic.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence between Sol Feinstone and Roman Rosdolsky, primarily in connection with Rosdolsky's manuscript "Friedrich Engeles und das Problem der Geschichtslosen Volker." This manuscript was first published in German in 1964 as Friedrich Engels und das Problem der "Geschictsloen" Volker (Die Nationalitatenfrage inder Revolution 1849-1849 im Lichte der "Neuen Rheinischen Zeitung"), and in English in 1986 as Engels and the "Nonhistoric" Peoples: The National Question in the Revolution of 1848. The collection also contains twenty-eight documents including signed letters by notable figures such as Eugene V. Debs, Petr Kropotkin, Vladimir Illich Lenin, and notes by Karl Marx. There are also approximately a dozen documents associated with the French Revolution and a surveyor's report from 1770 of Blidworth, England.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Sol Feinstone in 1959. The accession number associated with this gift is 1959.002.
Anarchists.; Socialists.; Germany |x History |y Revolution, 1848-1849.; France |x History |y Revolution, 1789-1799.; Signatures (names); Manuscripts for publication.; Feinstone, Sol, 1888-1980
- Series I: Papers, 1948-1950
  - Correspondence (regarding Roman Rosdolsky manuscript), 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Rosdolsky, Roman: Manuscript (I), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Rosdolsky, Roman: Manuscript (II), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II: Historical Documents
  - Antoinette, Marie, 1786 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bellamy, Edward, circa 1880 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - le Brun, Charles Francoise, 1800 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Debs, Eugene, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Fouquier-Tinville, Antoine Quentin, 1793 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Gohier, Louis Gerome, 1793 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Gorky, Maxim, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Herzen, Alexander, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hitler, Adolph, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Jomini, Antoine Henri, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Kropotkin, Petr, 1895-1909 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Laboulaye, Edouard Rene Lefebvre, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Lenin, Nickolai, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Louis XVI of France, 1781 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Marat, Jean Paul, 1797 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Marx, Karl, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Revelliere-Lepeaux, Louis Marie de la, 1813 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Riqueti, Honore Gabriel (comte de Mirabeau), 1775 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Robespierre, Maximillian, 1793 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Saliceti, Antoine Cristophe, 1796 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Surveyor's Report: Blidsworth, England, 1770 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Troupes Francaise, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Saint-Pierre, Jacques Henri Bernardin de, 1781 (Box 3)